Mrs. Humphreys Collection of Textile Related Photographs 6794 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Mrs. Humphreys Collection of Textile Related Photographs
1890- 1936
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Mrs. Humphreys
6794 P
1 folders
1 file folder
Gelatin silver print, photographs, graphics.
Mostly photographs of cyclone and flood damage in Lawrence, Massachusetts.
10062903
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 09, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, December 01, 2017
Scope and Contents
Includes photographs of the damage done by the July 26, 1890. This was either a tornado or microdownburst that left a path of destruction through South Lawrence, Massachusetts, 1,500 wide and two miles long. Over 200 buildings were damage and over 50 were destroyed. Also includes photographs of the March, 1936, flood in Lawrence, Massachusetts. Following heavy snow over the winter, heavy rain began on March 11, 1936, and continued for about two weeks. By the 13th mills in Lawrence began closing. The Merrimack River reached flood stage on March 20th, with a record 46.85 feet at the Lawrence Dam. The water continued to rise, reaching 48 feet on March 21st.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Canals; Chimneys; Cyclones; Disasters; Flood -- 1936; Flood damage; Floods; Lightning; Monuments; Parks; Railroad bridges; Skaters; Soldiers; Streets; Tailors; Textile factories; Tornado damage; Tornadoes; Woolen and worsted manufacture; Andover (Mass.); Balmoral Spa (Andover, Mass.); Essex Street (Lawrence, Mass.); Lawrence (Mass.); Tornadoes -- Massachusetts -- Lawrence -- 1890; Merrimack River Dam (Mass.); Shawsheen Village (Mass.); Arlington Mills; Pacific Mills; Wood Worsted Mill (Lawrence, Mass.)
10062903
- Disaster Photographs., 1890-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Item 1 is a photograph of a lithograph
  - Item 1: Wood Worsted Mills, Lawrence, Mass., 1905; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, [1905?]. Photograph of what was probably a photomechanical print. Image depicts the Wood Worsted Mills in Lawrence, Mass., shown with the Merrimack River on the left, a bridge crossing the river in the left foreground with horse-drawn wagons and pedestrians on it; a horse-drawn carriage, an early automobile, and pedestrians in front of the mill entrance on the right. Building is an extremely large six-story brick building, extending far down the river. The mill was demolished in 1958. 19.25 x 11.5 cm.
  - Item 2: Men stand on collapsed house after the Great Cyclone at Lawrence, Mass., 1890; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    July 26, 1890. Photo by A.W. Anderson, Haverhill, Mass. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a dozen or more men standing on or in front of a collapsed house after a tornado in Lawrence, Mass., on July 26, 1890. Bedding strewn in front of the house as well as a chair and other unrecognizable debris. 17.25 x 12 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 3: Collapsed house after the Great Cyclone at Lawrence, Mass., 1890; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    July 26, 1890. Photo by A.W. Anderson, Haverhill, Mass. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts workmen standing in front of a partially collapsed house after a tornado in Lawrence, Mass., on July 26, 1890. See item 2 in this folder for a view of this house after the wall had been pulled away, possibly by rescuers searching for victims. 17.25 x 12 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 4: Wreckage from the Great Cyclone at Lawrence, Mass., 1890; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    July 26, 1890. Photo by A.W. Anderson, Haverhill, Mass. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts wreckage from a collapsed building in the foreground; relatively untouched houses visible in background. Horse and wagon and several men visible in background. 17 x 12 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 5: Houses destroyed by the Great Cyclone at Lawrence, Mass., 1890; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    July 26, 1890. Photo by A.W. Anderson, Haverhill, Mass. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts houses destroyed by the tornado at Lawrence, Mass. House on the left has been completely turned upside down; house on the right is a pile of rubble. Several men and young boys stand in front of destroyed houses. For another view of these houses, see item 7 in this folder. 17 x 12.25 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 6: Overview of damage from the Great Cyclone at Lawrence, Mass., 1890; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    July 26, 1890. Photo by A.W. Anderson, Haverhill, Mass. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts houses destroyed by the tornado at Lawrence, Mass. House in center has collapsed in on itself; at right is part of a house; damage to house in rear clearly visible. Rubble strewn everywhere. 17 x 12 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 7: Upside down house after the Great Cyclone at Lawrence, Mass., 1890; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    July 26, 1890. Photo by A.W. Anderson, Haverhill, Mass. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a house turned upside down by the tornado in Lawrence, Mass. The first story is visible upside down; the second story may be the portion of the house at the right. Pile of rubble in the foreground. For another (better) view of this house see item 5 in this folder. 17 x 12.25 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 8: Houses opened up by the Great Cyclone at Lawrence, Mass., 1890; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    July 26, 1890. Photo by A.W. Anderson, Haverhill, Mass. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts two houses opened up by the tornado in Lawrence, Mass. The three-story house on the left has lost its roof, with one wall blown out showing the interior of the house. The two-story house house on the right suffered similar damage. Piles of lumber and wood strewn about. 17 x 12.25 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 9: North Main Street, Andover, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    North Main Street, Andover, Mass., during the flood of 1936. Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts a view of North Main Street in Andover, Mass., looking north, during the flood of 1936. Floodwaters are close to the bottom of the first floor doors; two men are standing in water nearly to their knees. 12.5 x 9.5 cm.
  - Item 10: Skaters on Merrimack River in front of the Arlington Mills, Lawrence, Mass., 1900; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, [ca 1900]. Image depicts skaters on the Merrimack River in Lawrence, Mass., with the Arlington Mills in the background. Quality of image is only fair; skaters are hard to see. 14 x 10 cm.
  - Item 11: Flood scene, Andover, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts a flood street scene, most probably in Andover, Mass. (Shawsheen Village?) during the flood of 1936. Water has reached the bottom step of the front door steps at each house, but the man standing in water in the center ground is almost up to his knees. Several other men stand on the steps at two different houses; two children play in the water's edge in the right background. 12 x 9.5 cm.
  - Item 12: Merrimack River, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, March 21, 1936. Image depicts the Merrimack River in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936. Note the level of rushing water is almost up to the bridge in the background. Railing alongside walkway (?) in foreground is partially underwater. Lawrence Dam is to the left, but the water level on either side of the dam is almost equal. Copy A. 17.5 x 12.25 cm.
  - Item 13: Lawrence Dam overflowing South Broadway, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, March 21, 1936. Image depicts the Lawrence Dam on the Merrimack River in Lawrence, Mass., with floodwaters overflowing South Broadway and running into the South Canal. Trailer or shed on the left is halfway under water. Note all the onlookers in the foreground watching the water rise. Copy A. 17.5 x 12.5 cm.
  - Item 14: Marston Street, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, March 21, 1936. Image depicts Marston Street in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, in the foreground. The houses inundated in the background are on River Street. Photograph taken from Prospect Hill. 17.5 x 12.5 cm.
  - Item 15: West of Falls Bridge, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts Merrimack River flooding west of the Falls Bridge in Lawrence, Mass., showing the Tool House underwater. Unclear who owns the "Tool House." 12.5 x 9.75 cm.
  - Item 16: Common Street, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts Common Street in Lawrence, Mass., just east of Hampshire Street, during the flood of 1936. Street is flooded; men standing in the street are knee-deep in water. Heavy, dump truck-type vehicle in center of street, another on the right. Common Street is four blocks north of the Merrimack River. 12 x 9.75 cm.
  - Item 17: Pumping station, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts the water (?) pumping station in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936. The station itself seems unscathed (on the right) but the two small buildings on the left and in the center are partially underwater. Note all the people clustered on land just in front of the pumping station; they may be filling sandbags, as there is a small line of sandbags visible. 12.5 x 10 cm.
  - Item 18: Ice going over the Lawrence, Dam, Lawrence, Mass., at night during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts ice chunks flowing over the Lawrence Dam on the Merrimack River in Lawrence, Mass., at night during the flood of 1936. 12.5 x 9.5 cm.
  - Item 19: Lowell Street, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts a section of Lowell Street near the intersection of Oxford Street in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936. Cars in the center drive through some water in the street, but further in the background, Lowell Street remains dry. Lowell Street runs roughly parallel to the Merrimack River but is six blocks north of the river. 12.5 x 9.5 cm.
  - Item 20: Intersection of Essex and Lawrence streets, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts a view of the intersection of Essex and Lawrence streets in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936. The water appears deeper in the foreground, splashing over car tires, but the street appears dry in the background. This intersection is three blocks north of the Merrimack River. See also item 23 in this folder. 12.5 x 10 cm.
  - Item 21: Warner Bros. Theatre, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts the Warner Bros. Theatre, a movie theater located at 1 Lawrence Street in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936. Two men stand in front of the theater but the floodwaters have virtually reached the theater doors. 12 x 10 cm.
  - Item 22: B&M Station underpass, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts the Boston & Maine Railroad station underpass in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936. A railroad engine is pulling a railroad car (or more) over the underpass, but floodwaters underneath have reached nearly to the roofs of the cars parked on the left. 12.75 x 10 cm.
  - Item 23: Corner of Essex and Lawrence streets, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts a view of the intersection of Essex and Lawrence streets in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, taken from a high angle, probably the upper floor in a nearby building. Cars and buses navigate the intersection which has partially filled with water. Note the large number of pedestrians on either side of the street. This intersection is three blocks north of the Merrimack River. See also item 20 in this folder. 12 x 9.5 cm.
  - Item 24: Lawrence Common fountain frozen in winter, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, 1893. Image depicts a fountain on the Lawrence Common in Lawrence, Mass., frozen in the winter of 1893. 11 x 15.75 cm.
  - Item 25: High water at the railroad bridge, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts a view of the high water at the railroad bridge in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936. This bridge, formally known as the Manchester and Lawrence Railroad Bridge, is just downstream on the Merrimack River from the Lawrence Dam. The floodwaters have reached to the flooring of the bridge, leaving the railroad coal cars on the bridge very close to being overtaken by the river. 12.5 x 9.5 cm.
  - Item 26: Lawrence Dam on the Merrimack River from the north side, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts a view of the Merrimack River at the Lawrence Dam in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, taken from the north side of the river. Water rushing over the dam (from right to left) is virtually crashing into the bridge, just downstream of the dam. See item 27 in this folder for a view of the dam from the south side taken a day later. 12.5 x 9.5 cm.
  - Item 27: Lawrence Dam on the Merrimack River from the south side, Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, March 21, 1936. Image depicts a view of the Merrimack River at the Lawrence Dam in Lawrence, Mass., during the flood of 1936, taken from the south side of the river. Water rushing over the dam (on the left) is virtually even with the floodwaters on the right. Written on the reverse: "Dam from South Side - Water eventually overran this territory." See item 26 in this folder for a view of the dam from the north side taken a day earlier. Copy A. 17.5 x 12.5 cm.
  - Item 28: Balmoral Spa, Shawsheen Village, Andover, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 20, 1936. Image depicts the Balmoral Spa in Shawsheen Village (part of Andover, Mass.) during the flood of 1936. Water has reached halfway up the first-floor windows. Several men in a rowboat in the left background. See item 29 in this folder for a view taken a day later. 12 x 9.25 cm.
  - Item 29: Shawsheen Square, Shawsheen Village, Andover, Mass., during the flood of 1936, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, March 21, 1936. Image depicts the Balmoral Spa (left background) and Shawsheen Square in Shawsheen Village (part of Andover, Mass.) during the flood of 1936. Water is now about three-quarters of the way up the first-floor windows. See item 28 in this folder for a view of the Spa taken a day earlier. Written on reverse of photo: "Shawsheen Square - Water was later as high as the bottom of the light on Silent Policeman." The Silent Policeman is probably the marker in the center right labeled "Slow Keep Right" which would indicate that the water rose at least one foot higher than seen here. 17.5 x 9.25 cm.